"How Well Do Medicines Like Fosamax Work
to Treat Osteoporosis?"
Drug therapy for osteoporosis
is recommended
for those 50 and older
with a history of past hip
or spine fractures,
those with hip or spine
"T-scores"
of negative 2.5 or less,
and postmenopausal women
or men 50 and older
who don't make that cut-off
but have an estimated
20 percent or higher risk
of a major osteoporotic fracture
over the subsequent decade,
or an estimated
3 percent or greater risk
of hip fracture, specifically.
A T-score is a measure
of how dense your bones are
compared to
a 30-year-old white woman.
Since that's the standard,
and we tend to lose bone
as we age,
you can be labeled
as having osteoporosis
even if you have completely
normal bone density
for your age.
Of course, just because your
bone density may be normal
doesn't mean
it's necessarily optimal,
which is why the National
Osteoporosis Foundation
set out these guidelines
for drug treatment.
Though another reason, perhaps,
is because it gets
substantial funding
from the drug industry,
which rakes in literally
billions of dollars in profits
from osteoporosis drugs.
What does the science say?
The primary drug class
used to treat osteoporosis
is the bisphosphonates,
sold as such brands as Fosamax,
Actonel, Boniva, and Reclast.
They are most effective at
reducing vertebral fractures,
cutting the risk
in postmenopausal women
from 2.8 percent
down to 1.4 percent.
That's a relative risk
reduction of 50 percent,
but an absolute risk
reduction of only 1.4 percent,
meaning you'd have to treat
71 women to prevent
just one woman from getting
a vertebral fracture.
Unfortunately, the diagnosis
of vertebral fracture
is kind of wishy-washy.
Depending on how you define
the changes on x-ray,
the prevalence
of vertebral fractures
can vary as much as
3 percent to 90 percent
in the same elderly population--
almost none to almost all.
They're also poorly predictive
of back pain or disability.
Vertebral fractures can
certainly lead to back pain
and reduced physical function,
but only about a third
are symptomatic at all.
The most harmful fractures
are hip fractures.
Despite most
of the clinical trials
for osteoporosis treatment
being funded by the drug
companies themselves,
no primary prevention benefit
from bisphosphonates
has been found
for hip fractures.
In other words,
taking these drugs
has not been convincingly shown
to prevent fracturing your hip
in the first place.
However, having a prior fracture
doubles your risk
of breaking another bone,
so, for those at high risk,
bisphosphonate drugs
may decrease the odds
of hip fracture by 25 percent,
though the absolute
risk reduction is, again,
only about 1 percent.
It may take treating 91 people
for three years
to prevent one hip fracture.
An overconfidence in the power
of pills and procedures
for disease prevention
may be one of the reasons
doctors and patients alike
may undervalue diet
and lifestyle approaches.
In this study,
patients were asked to estimate
the number of fractures
or deaths prevented
in a group of 5,000 patients
undergoing each
drug intervention
over a period of 10 years.
The vast majority of people
tended to wildly overestimate
the ability of mammograms
and colonoscopies
to prevent cancer deaths,
the power of drugs like Fosamax
to prevent hip fractures,
and drugs like Lipitor
to prevent fatal heart attacks.
No wonder most people continue
to rely on drugs to save them.
But the dirty little secret is
that most people said
they wouldn't be willing
to take many of these drugs
if they knew how little benefit
these products actually offered.
In a study of those undergoing
bone density scans,
the average five-year
fracture risk
that would motivate
most participants
to consider preventative
medicine was 50 to 60 percent,
much higher
than their actual risk.
Most patients want
to be told the truth.
They want to be told
what the chances are
that the drugs will
actually benefit them,
but there is a tension between
the patient's right to know
and the likely reduction
in their willingness
to take the drug
if they knew the truth.
In the bone density scan survey,
participants
greatly overestimated
their own personal risk
for hip fracture,
thinking it was
around 19 percent
over the next 5 years,
which is more than
ten times higher
than their actual risk
of 1.4 percent.
Rather than disabusing them
of this overestimate,
some suggest physicians
should do the opposite:
stoke fear in patients
who "refuse to comply with
medication recommendations"
by increasing their
"perceived susceptibility
to fragility fractures"
as well as their
"perceived severity of suffering
from a fragility fracture."
Since emotion can be more
motivating than reason
and anecdotal evidence
can be more effective
than evidence-evidence,
a "graphic scenario
of suffering and incapacitation
after a hip fracture
will enhance emotional
perception of this threat."
But hip fractures
can indeed be devastating
and are associated
with a significant risk
of ensuing death.
So, what about all of the lives
these drugs must be saving?
Well, only about a quarter of
the deaths following fractures
may be attributable
to the fracture itself,
so most of the mortality risk
may just be a consequence
of the comorbidities--
that is, the other diseases
and poor health status
of people who tend
to fracture their hips.
So, they might have died anyway
in that same time frame
even if they hadn't
broken any bones.
This may help explain
why there are no saved lives.
Osteoporosis drug treatments,
particularly bisphosphonates,
fail to significantly reduce
overall mortality.